<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>The Big Sleep</title>
	<atom:link href="https://galgorium.github.io/TheBigSleep/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://galgorium.github.io/TheBigSleep/</link>
	<description>Shadows in the City of Angels</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 16:33:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>es</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://galgorium.github.io/TheBigSleep/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/cropped-favicon-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>The Big Sleep</title>
	<link>https://galgorium.github.io/TheBigSleep/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>This was the film in which Bogart became Marlowe for all time&#8230;</title>
		<link>https://galgorium.github.io/TheBigSleep/this-was-the-film-in-which-bogart-became-marlowe-for-all-time/</link>
					<comments>https://galgorium.github.io/TheBigSleep/this-was-the-film-in-which-bogart-became-marlowe-for-all-time/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[firmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2024 15:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://galgorium.github.io/TheBigSleep/?p=125</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Frequently compared with Huston&#8217;s «The Maltese Falcon» as one of the classics of the private eye genre, «The Big Sleep» is, in many ways, far removed from the former film Where on the contrary «The Maltese Falcon» has a basically simple plot about the hunt for a priceless statuette, «The Big Sleep» has probably the...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Frequently compared with Huston&#8217;s «The Maltese Falcon» as one of the classics of the private eye genre, «The Big Sleep» is, in many ways, far removed from the former film Where on the contrary «The Maltese Falcon» has a basically simple plot about the hunt for a priceless statuette, «The Big Sleep» has probably the most complicated story ever filmed And, more important, where Hammett&#8217;s Sam Spade was uncompromising, mercenary and a winner, Raymond Chandlers Philip Marlowe was a frequent sufferer at the hands of cops and hoods and in many ways a loser</p>



<p>«The Big Sleep» almost defies plot analysis Just about the only part of the film that is straightforward is the opening sequence when Marlowe undertakes a job of investigation for a crippled millionaire whose daughter is being blackmailed Afterwards it fills up with such a vast assortment of shadowy characters  whores, pimps, killers, gamblers, a dope hooked deb who sucks her thumb  it is almost impossible to follow Nevertheless let me mention that Bogart was hired ostensibly to track down a blackmailer, but quickly finds himself immersed in murder, and harmonized double-crosses</p>



<p>The film has speed, efficiency and magnificent craftsmanship, it has wit and the acting, needless to say, is of the quality one expects from a Warner&#8217;s movie of the Forties Bogart witnesses Bob Steele smilingly giving Elisha Cook, Jr., a poisoned glass of water, all the while assuring him that he has nothing to fear; and Bogart&#8217;s coldly calculated shootout with Steele later in the film Bacall moves stealthily in fear or shame, Martha Vickers expresses displeasure, resentment, and bad humor, chief heavy John Ridgeley shows anger and Elisha Cook Jr. is furtive</p>



<p>If the magic, whether it was entirely calculated in advance or not, lies in the absolute congruence of the Marlowe character with Bogart&#8217;s screen personality, it nevertheless was an important contribution to the Bogart mystique and is usually paired with «The Maltese Falcon» when reissued</p>



<p>This was the film in which Bogart became Marlowe for all time… It was the only time he played Marlowe, but it stuck Bogart as Marlowe is a rock of logic in a carousel of shady characters with clear psychological motivations for only partially explained actions…</p>



<p>When it first appeared, «The Big Sleep» was attacked in some quarters for violence and amorality but beneath its cynicism and toughness there breathed a heart and sentimentality which he1p to make it timeless</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://galgorium.github.io/TheBigSleep/this-was-the-film-in-which-bogart-became-marlowe-for-all-time/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lots of murders never looked and sounded to good</title>
		<link>https://galgorium.github.io/TheBigSleep/lots-of-murders-never-looked-and-sounded-to-good/</link>
					<comments>https://galgorium.github.io/TheBigSleep/lots-of-murders-never-looked-and-sounded-to-good/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[firmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2024 16:58:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://galgorium.github.io/TheBigSleep/?p=132</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Even hardened film noir and Humphrey Bogart fans admit that this is one confusing movie. It makes sense, but it is edited down to such essentials, and it barrels along with the intensity of a bullet in a smoky canyon using overlapping dialog e and a shower of names, half of whom end up dead,...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Even hardened film noir and Humphrey Bogart fans admit that this is one confusing movie. It makes sense, but it is edited down to such essentials, and it barrels along with the intensity of a bullet in a smoky canyon using overlapping dialog e and a shower of names, half of whom end up dead, it&#8217;s really an impossible job for a mortal viewer.</p>



<p>And that&#8217;s where it&#8217;s aura, and magic, and legend, lie. It&#8217;s a great film, and if it&#8217;s flawed by its excessive velocity, it&#8217;s defined by it, too. Enjoy Bogart as such, and Lauren Bacall for her sporadic appearances, and for Elisha Cook Jr. for a brief, wonderful splash. All the side characters, even the ones who are clearly only characters, are dripping with criminal drama. The photography is dark but never obscure, the action is fast but never unreasonable, and the lines are classic noir.</p>



<p>In fact, the dialog, if you are paying attention, is one of the gems of 1940s movies&#8211;really witty and cutting, and cunning. The movie is brilliant top to bottom, if only you could keep track of what was going on.</p>



<p>Suggestions: Read the plot in the Wikipedia entry before you watch the movie a second time. (The first time, just dive and and get lost. It&#8217;s too much fun to care, if you can let go.) Watch Bogart&#8217;s delivery, his physical presence, his wherewithal. Listen to Bacall sing (pretty darned good). Watch the amazing light and camera work (Sydney Hickox) with it&#8217;s constantly moving perspective and layers of action. Follow the score (Max Steiner) which is appropriately restrained, turning just slightly when Bogart and Bacall are in scenes together.</p>



<p>Howard Hawks pulls of a quirky masterpiece here. You get to the end and frankly don&#8217;t care too much, perhaps, about the outcome, about who survives and what their futures might hold. But that&#8217;s fine, too. It might just make you want to watch it again. Good filmmaking does that.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://galgorium.github.io/TheBigSleep/lots-of-murders-never-looked-and-sounded-to-good/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>My head&#8217;s still spinning</title>
		<link>https://galgorium.github.io/TheBigSleep/my-heads-still-spinning/</link>
					<comments>https://galgorium.github.io/TheBigSleep/my-heads-still-spinning/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[firmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 Sep 2023 16:00:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://galgorium.github.io/TheBigSleep/?p=134</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[THE BIG SLEEP is one of the more entertaining private eye movies I have seen. A dying old man has two beautiful, uncontrollable daughters: Vivien (Lauren Bacall), and Carmen (Martha Vickers). Carmen is being blackmailed, and her father hires P.I. Christopher Marlowe (the beloved Humphrey Bogart) to get the blackmailer off her back. But Marlowe...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>THE BIG SLEEP is one of the more entertaining private eye movies I have seen. A dying old man has two beautiful, uncontrollable daughters: Vivien (Lauren Bacall), and Carmen (Martha Vickers). Carmen is being blackmailed, and her father hires P.I. Christopher Marlowe (the beloved Humphrey Bogart) to get the blackmailer off her back. But Marlowe finds that somebody else has done this job for him: the blackmailer is murdered almost under his nose. And as he puts it, «That didn&#8217;t stop things. That just starts &#8216;em.»</p>



<p>I have not read Raymond Chandler&#8217;s novel, on which this movie was based, but those who have say the title refers to death. That is never explained in the movie. Howard Hawks packs so much plot into 114 minutes of footage that the movie feels like it&#8217;s bursting at the seams. The story is not incomprehensible as some would have it; while there are many improbable coincidences, there is no element I can point to and say «That couldn&#8217;t have happened.» (Although I&#8217;m still not quite sure how Carmen got into Marlowe&#8217;s apartment). True, the plot really is very hard to follow, and Marlowe&#8217;s periodic explanations of events, without which the movie would indeed be nonsensical, smack more of inspired guesswork than logical deduction. But the furious pace at which the plot unfolds lends more excitement to the movie than nine out of ten of today&#8217;s lazily plotted would-be thrillers.</p>



<p>THE BIG SLEEP&#8217;s greatest strength is its delightfully droll dialogue. When Chandler writes the novel and then Faulkner helps adapt it, you expect some verbal fireworks, and you sure do get them. «How do you like your brandy?» «In a glass.» &#8211; «You&#8217;re not very tall, are you?» «I try to be.» &#8211; «I&#8217;m getting cuter every minute.» &#8211; «Such a lot of guns around town, and so few brains.» &#8211; «Is it any of your business?» «I could make it my business.» «I could make your business mine.» «You wouldn&#8217;t like it. The pay&#8217;s too small.» &#8211; «She tried to sit in my lap while I was standing up.» Bogie and Bacall get two of the best exchanges; they have a horse-racing discussion where racy double-entendres are dripping like savory sauce off of every word, and they also get a truly hilarious telephone conversation where Marlowe convinces Vivien not to call the police.</p>



<p>But THE BIG SLEEP has a harder side that is also effective. It is shockingly violent for a movie produced under the stern eyes of the Hayes code censors. The movie is too unpredictable to generate much suspense (you can&#8217;t dread something you don&#8217;t know is going to happen), but the ending is one of the most intense, nailbiting scenes you&#8217;ll ever see.</p>



<p>The 1940s were not a great era for film music, which makes Max Steiner&#8217;s brooding score all the more impressive. The print I saw was very low-quality, so I can&#8217;t judge the cinematography.</p>



<p>The acting is wonderful. Bogart gets to show his chops at one point by switching off the hard-boiled personality he developed for THE MALTESE FALCON and impersonating an antiquarian bookworm. Bacall radiates class whether she&#8217;s at ease smoking in a cafe or outwitting a man holding her at gunpoint. Martha Vickers&#8217; Carmen strikes the perfect balance of appealing seductiveness and outright nastiness.</p>



<p>One final note: this movie is almost Bond-like in terms of the number of appallingly beautiful women Marlowe accidentally encounters, all of whom seem to have a burning desire for him. Even his taxi driver wants him. Dorothy Malone, whose character name we never learn, plays the sexiest book seller you will ever meet (and yes, she wears glasses; eat your heart out, Dorothy Parker!). Minus fifty points for credibility, plus a hundred points for entertainment. Regrettably, I cannot promise similar thrills for the female audience; it just kind of depends on how you like Men In Suits.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://galgorium.github.io/TheBigSleep/my-heads-still-spinning/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
